long before the due date. That proves that this species of humanity is capable of achieving extraordinary progress if it really acts together and it really tries hard. But if I had to put it in a nutshell these days, I sort of feel that globalization has taken us by surprise, and we've been slow to respond to it. If you look at the downside of globalization, it really does seem to be sometimes overwhelming. All of the grand challenges that we face today, like climate change and human rights and demographics and terrorism and pandemics and narco-trafficking and human slavery and species loss, I could go on, we're not making an awful lot of progress against an awful lot of those challenges. So in a nutshell, that's the challenge that we all face today at this interesting point in history. That's clearly what we've got to do next. We've somehow got to get our act together and we've got to figure out how to globalize the solutions better so that we don't simply become a species which is the victim of the globalization of problems. Why are we so slow at achieving these advances? What's the reason for it? Well, there are, of course, a number of reasons, but perhaps the primary reason is because we're still organized as a species in the same way that we were organized 200 or 300 years ago. There's one superpower left on the planet and that is the seven billion people, the seven billion of us who cause all these problems, the same seven billion, by the way, who will resolve them all. But how are those seven billion organized? They're still organized in 200 or so nation-states, and the nations have governments that make rules and cause us to behave in certain ways. And that's a pretty efficient system, but the problem is that the way that those laws are made and the way those governments think is absolutely wrong for the solution of global problems, because it all looks inwards. The politicians that we elect and the politicians we don't elect, on the whole, have minds that microscope. They don't have minds that telescope. They look in. They pretend, they behave, as if they believed that every country was an island that existed quite happily, independently of all the others on its own little planet in its own little solar system. This is the problem: countries competing against each other, countries fighting against each other. This week, as any week you care to look at, you'll find people actually trying to kill each other from country to country, but even when that's not going on, there's competition between countries, each one trying to shaft the next. This is clearly not a good arrangement. We clearly need to change it. We clearly need to find ways of encouraging countries to start working together a little bit better. And why won't they do that? Why is it that our leaders still persist in looking inwards? Well, the first and most obvious reason is because that's what we ask them to do. That's what we tell them to do. When we elect governments or when we tolerate unelected governments, we're effectively telling them that what we want is for them to deliver us in our country a certain number of things. We want them to deliver prosperity, growth, competitiveness, transparency, justice and all of those things. So unless we start asking our governments to think outside a little bit, to consider the global problems that will finish us all if we don't start considering them, then we can hardly blame them if what they carry on doing is looking inwards, if they still have minds that microscope rather than minds that telescope. That's the first reason why things tend not to change. The second reason is that these governments, just like all the rest of us, are cultural psychopaths. I don't mean to be rude, but you know what a psychopath is. A psychopath is a person who, unfortunately for him or her, lacks the ability to really empathize with other human beings. When they look around, they don't see other human beings with deep, rich, three-dimensional personal lives and aims and ambitions. What they see is cardboard cutouts, and it's very sad and it's very lonely, and it's very rare, fortunately. But actually, aren't most of us not really so very good at empathy? Oh sure, we're very good at empathy when it's a question of dealing with people who kind of look like us and kind of walk and talk and eat and pray and wear like us, but when it comes to people who don't do that, who don't quite dress like us and don't quite pray like us and don't quite talk like us, do we not also have a tendency to see them ever so slightly as cardboard cutouts too? And this is a question we need to ask ourselves. I think constantly we have to monitor it. Are we and our politicians to a degree cultural psychopaths? The third reason is hardly worth mentioning because it's so silly, but there's a belief amongst governments that the domestic agenda and the international agenda are incompatible and always will be. This is just nonsense. In my day job, I'm a policy adviser. I've spent the last 15 years or so advising governments around the world, and in all of that time I have never once seen a single domestic policy issue that could not be more imaginatively, effectively and rapidly resolved than by treating it as an international problem, looking at the international context, comparing what others have done, bringing in others, working externally instead of working internally. And so you may say, well, given all of that, why then doesn't it work? Why can we not make our politicians change? Why can't we demand them? Well I, like a lot of us, spend a lot of time complaining about how hard it is to make people change, and I don't think we should fuss about it. I think we should just accept that we are an inherently conservative species. We don't like to change. It exists for very sensible evolutionary reasons. We probably wouldn't still be here today if we weren't so resistant to change. It's very simple: Many thousands of years ago, we discovered that if we carried on doing the same things, we wouldn't die, because the things that we've done before by definition didn't kill us, and therefore as long as we carry on doing them, we'll be okay, and it's very sensible not to do anything new, because it might kill you. But of course, there are exceptions to that. Otherwise, we'd never get anywhere. And one of the exceptions, the interesting exception, is when you can show to people that there might be some self-interest in them making that leap of faith and changing a little bit. So I've spent a lot of the last 10 or 15 years trying to find out what could be that self-interest that would encourage not just politicians but also businesses and general populations, all of us, to start to think a little more outwardly, to think in a bigger picture, not always to look inwards, sometimes to look outwards. And this is where I discovered something quite important. In 2005, I launched a study called the Nation Brands Index. What it is, it's a very large-scale study that polls a very large sample of the world's population, a sample that represents about 70 percent of the planet's population, and I started asking them a series of questions about how they perceive other countries. And the Nation Brands Index over the years has grown to be a very, very large database. It's about 200 billion data points tracking what ordinary people think about other countries and why. Why did I do this? Well, because the governments that I advise are very, very keen on knowing how they are regarded. They've known, partly because I've encouraged them to realize it, that countries depend enormously on their reputations in order to survive and prosper in the world. If a country has a great, positive image, like Germany has or Sweden or Switzerland, everything is easy and everything is cheap. You get more tourists. You get more investors. You sell your products more expensively. If, on the other hand, you have a country with a very weak or a very negative image, everything is difficult and everything is expensive. So governments care desperately about the image of their country, because it makes a direct difference to how much money they can make, and that's what they've promised their populations they're going to deliver. So a couple of years ago, I thought I would take some time out and speak to that gigantic database and ask it, why do some people prefer one country more than another? And the answer that the database gave me completely staggered me. It was 6.8. I haven't got time to explain in detail. Basically what it told me was — (Laughter) (Applause) — the kinds of countries we prefer are good countries. We don't admire countries primarily because they're rich, because they're powerful, because they're successful, because they're modern, because they're technologically advanced. We primarily admire countries that are good. What do we mean by good? We mean countries that seem to contribute something to the world in which we live, countries that actually make the world safer or better or richer or fairer. Those are the countries we like. This is a discovery of significant importance — you see where I'm going — because it squares the circle. I can now say, and often do, to any government, in order to do well, you need to do good. If you want to sell more products, if you want to get more investment, if you want to become more competitive, then you need to start behaving, because that's why people will respect you and do business with you, and therefore, the more you collaborate, the more competitive you become. This is quite an important discovery, and as soon as I discovered this, I felt another index coming on. I swear that as I get older, my ideas become simpler and more and more childish. This one is called the Good Country Index, and it does exactly what it says on the tin. It measures, or at least it tries to measure, exactly how much each country on Earth contributes not to its own population but to the rest of humanity. Bizarrely, nobody had ever thought of measuring this before. So my colleague Dr. Robert Govers and I have spent the best part of the last two years, with the help of a large number of very serious and clever people, cramming together all the reliable data in the world we could find about what countries give to the world. And you're waiting for me to tell you which one comes top. And I'm going to tell you, but first of all I want to tell you precisely what I mean when I say a good country. I do not mean morally good. When I say that Country X is the goodest country on Earth, and I mean goodest, I don't mean best. Best is something different. When you're talking about a good country, you can be good, gooder and goodest. It's not the same thing as good, better and best. This is a country which simply gives more to humanity than any other country. I don't talk about how they behave at home because that's measured elsewhere. And the winner is Ireland. (Applause) According to the data here, no country on Earth, per head of population, per dollar of GDP, contributes more to the world that we live in than Ireland. What does this mean? This means that as we go to sleep at night, all of us in the last 15 seconds before we drift off to sleep, our final thought should be, godammit, I'm glad that Ireland exists. (Laughter) And that — (Applause) — In the depths of a very severe economic recession, I think that there's a really important lesson there, that if you can remember your international obligations whilst you are trying to rebuild your own economy, that's really something. Finland ranks pretty much the same. The only reason why it's below Ireland is because its lowest score is lower than Ireland's lowest score. Now the other thing you'll notice about the top 10 there is, of course, they're all, apart from New Zealand, Western European nations. They're also all rich. This depressed me, because one of the things that I did not want to discover with this index is that it's purely the province of rich countries to help poor countries. This is not what it's all about. And indeed, if you look further down the list, I don't have the slide here, you will see something that made me very happy indeed, that Kenya is in the top 30, and that demonstrates one very, very important thing. This is not about money. This is about attitude. This is about culture. This is about a government and a people that care about the rest of the world and have the imagination and the courage to think outwards instead of only thinking selfishly. I'm going to whip through the other slides just so you can see some of the lower-lying countries. There's Germany at 13th, the U.S. comes 21st, Mexico comes 66th, and then we have some of the big developing countries, like Russia at 95th, China at 107th. Countries like China and Russia and India, which is down in the same part of the index, well, in some ways, it's not surprising. They've spent a great deal of time over the last decades building their own economy, building their own society and their own polity, but it is to be hoped that the second phase of their growth will be somewhat more outward-looking than the first phase has been so far. And then you can break down each country in terms of the actual datasets that build into it. I'll allow you to do that. From midnight tonight it's going to be on goodcountry.org, and you can look at the country. You can look right down to the level of the individual datasets. Now that's the Good Country Index. What's it there for? Well, it's there really because I want to try to introduce this word, or reintroduce this word, into the discourse. I've had enough hearing about competitive countries. I've had enough hearing about prosperous, wealthy, fast-growing countries. I've even had enough hearing about happy countries because in the end that's still selfish. That's still about us, and if we carry on thinking about us, we are in deep, deep trouble. I think we all know what it is that we want to hear about. We want to hear about good countries, and so I want to ask you all a favor. I'm not asking a lot. It's something that you might find easy to do and you might even find enjoyable and even helpful to do, and that's simply to start using the word "good" in this context. When you think about your own country, when you think about other people's countries, when you think about companies, when you talk about the world that we live in today, start using that word in the way that I've talked about this evening. Not good, the opposite of bad, because that's an argument that never finishes. Good, the opposite of selfish, good being a country that thinks about all of us. That's what I would like you to do, and I'd like you to use it as a stick with which to beat your politicians. When you elect them, when you reelect them, when you vote for them, when you listen to what they're offering you, use that word, "good," and ask yourself, "Is that what a good country would do?" And if the answer is no, be very suspicious. Ask yourself, is that the behavior of my country? Do I want to come from a country where the government, in my name, is doing things like that? Or do I, on the other hand, prefer the idea of walking around the world with my head held high thinking, "Yeah, I'm proud to come from a good country"? And everybody will welcome you. And everybody in the last 15 seconds before they drift off to sleep at night will say, "Gosh, I'm glad that person's country exists." Ultimately, that, I think, is what will make the change. That word, "good," and the number 6.8 and the discovery that's behind it have changed my life. I think they can change your life, and I think we can use it to change the way that our politicians and our companies behave, and in doing so, we can change the world. I've started thinking very differently about my own country since I've been thinking about these things. I used to think that I wanted to live in a rich country, and then I started thinking I wanted to live in a happy country, but I began to realize, it's not enough. I don't want to live in a rich country. I don't want to live in a fast-growing or competitive country. I want to live in a good country, and I so, so hope that you do too. Thank you. (Applause)
bien avant l'échéance. Cela prouve que l'espèce humaine peut arriver à d'extraordinaires progrès en se montrant unie et persévérante. Mais en ce moment, j'ai l'impression que la mondialisation nous a pris par surprise, et que nous y avons réagi lentement. Si l'on regarde ses inconvénients C'est vrai que ça peut sembler accablant. Tous les problèmes auxquels nous faisons face, comme le réchauffement planétaire, les droits de l'Homme, la surpopulation, le terrorisme, les épidémies, le trafic de drogue, l'esclavage, la disparition des espèces, et plus encore ; nous ne progressons pas beaucoup sur beaucoup de ces problèmes. En bref, c'est le problème qui se pose à nous tous en cette période-clé de l'histoire. C'est ce que nous devons faire. Il faut que nous arrivions à nous reprendre et trouver comment améliorer la mondialisation des solutions pour éviter de devenir une espèce victime de la mondialisation des problèmes. Mais, alors, pourquoi notre progrès est-il si lent ? Quelle en est la raison ? Bien sûr, il y a plusieurs raisons, mais c'est peut-être surtout parce que notre espèce est toujours organisée de la même façon qu'il y a 200 ou 300 ans. Il y a une superpuissance sur Terre : les sept milliards que nous sommes, qui créent tous ces problèmes, les mêmes, d'ailleurs, qui les régleront tous. Mais comment ces sept milliards sont-ils organisés ? Ils sont toujours organisés en environ 200 États-nations, et les nations ont des gouvernements qui créent des lois et nous font nous comporter d'une certaine façon. Et c'est un système assez efficace, sauf que la façon de créer ces lois et la façon de penser des gouvernements ne permettent pas de résoudre des problèmes globaux, parce qu'elles se centrent sur leur nation. Les politiciens élus, et ceux non élus, en général, regardent dans un microscope. Pas dans un télescope. Ils se concentrent sur eux-mêmes. Ils prétendent, se comportent, comme s'ils pensaient que chaque pays était une île qui vivait heureuse et indépendante de toutes les autres sur sa petite planète à elle dans son petit système solaire. Voilà le problème : des pays en compétition, des pays en guerre. Cette semaine, comme toujours, vous verrez des gens essayer de s'entretuer d'un pays à l'autre, et même quand ce n'est pas le cas, les pays sont en compétition, chacun essayant de rouler l'autre. Ce n'est pas une bonne situation. Elle ne peut pas durer. Nous devons trouver des façons d'encourager les pays à collaborer d'une meilleure façon. Et pourquoi ne le font-ils pas? Pourquoi nos dirigeants persistent-ils dans cette approche égocentriste ? Tout d'abord, évidemment, c'est que nous le leur demandons. C'est notre message. En élisant un gouvernement ou en tolérant un gouvernement illégitime, nous leur disons que ce que nous voulons, c'est qu'ils arrivent à certaines choses dans notre pays. Nous voulons qu'ils assurent la prospérité, la croissance, la compétitivité, la transparence, la justice, etc. Si l'on ne demande pas à nos gouvernements de changer un peu d'approche, de réfléchir aux problèmes qui nous tueront tous si nous ne les réglons pas rapidement, alors on ne peut pas vraiment leur reprocher de continuer à se centrer sur eux-mêmes, à regarder dans un microscope plutôt que dans un télescope. C'est la première raison du peu de changements. La deuxième, c'est que ces gouvernements, tout comme nous tous, sont des psychopathes culturels. Ne le prenez pas mal, mais vous le savez. Un psychopathe est quelqu'un qui, malheureusement, n'a pas la capacité de compatir avec d'autres êtres humains. Autour d'eux, ils ne voient pas des semblables, avec des vies remplies, à trois dimensions, des buts et des ambitions. Ils voient des personnages en carton, ils se sentent tristes et seuls, et heureusement, c'est très rare. Mais, en fait, ne sommes-nous pas, pour la plupart, pas très bons pour l'empathie? Si, bien sûr, quand il s'agit de personnes qui nous ressemblent, marchent, parlent, mangent, prient et s'habillent comme nous, mais pour les autres personnes, qui s'habillent différemment, prient différemment, et parlent différemment, n'avons-nous pas la même tendance à les voir comme des personnages en carton ? Il faut se poser cette question. Je pense qu'il faut sans cesse se demander si nous ne sommes pas, d'une certaine façon, des psychopathes culturels. Troisièmement, c'est bête, c'est ridicule, mais nos dirigeants pensent que l'agenda national et l'agenda international sont incompatibles et le resteront. C'est du grand n'importe quoi. Je suis conseiller politique. J'ai passé les 15 dernières années à conseiller divers gouvernements, et, pendant ces années, jamais je n'ai vu un seul problème national qui ne pouvait être résolu de façon plus inventive, plus efficace et plus rapide qu'en le traitant comme un problème international, en se tournant vers l'international, en regardant ce que les autres font, en se tournant vers l'extérieur plutôt que vers l'intérieur. Vous allez me dire, eh bien alors, pourquoi ça ne marche pas ? Pourquoi nos politiciens ne changent-ils pas ? Comment les y obliger ? Comme tout le monde, je passe beaucoup de temps à dire qu'il est difficile de faire changer quelqu'un, et nous ne devrions pas nous en plaindre. Nous devrions accepter d'être une espèce conservatrice par nature. Nous n'aimons pas le changement. C'est la conséquence logique de notre évolution. Nous n'existerions sûrement plus aujourd'hui si nous n'étions pas si anti-changement. C'est tout simple : il y a des milliers d'années, nous avons découvert qu'en continuant à faire les mêmes choses, nous pourrions survivre, car ce que nous avons fait par le passé ne nous a bien sûr pas tués, et donc en continuant à faire de même, tout ira bien, et refuser le changement est logique puisqu'il pourrait nous tuer. Mais, bien sûr, il existe des exceptions, sinon, on n'avancerait jamais. Et on est dans un cas exceptionnel quand on arrive à montrer qu'il pourrait y avoir un intérêt personnel à faire ce saut dans le vide et à changer un peu les choses. J'ai donc passé ces 15 dernières années à chercher quel pourrait être cet intérêt personnel qui n'encouragerait pas que les politiciens mais aussi les entreprises et le public, nous tous, à penser un peu plus vers l'extérieur, à voir les choses d'un peu plus loin, de ne pas regarder uniquement vers soi, mais aussi vers les autres. Et c'est là que j'ai fait une découverte assez importante. En 2005, j'ai lancé une étude, l'indice des marques nationales. C'est une étude à grande échelle qui pose des questions à un grand échantillon de la population, un échantillon représentant environ 70% de la population mondiale, et j'ai décidé de leur poser des questions sur leurs perceptions des autres pays. Et l'indice des marques nationales est alors devenu une immense base de données. On a récolté environ 200 milliards de données reflétant ce que les gens ordinaires pensent des autres pays et pourquoi. À quoi bon ? Parce que les gouvernements que je conseille veulent vraiment savoir comment ils sont perçus. Ils savent, notamment parce que je les ai incités à le comprendre, que les pays dépendent énormément de leurs réputations afin de survivre et de prospérer dans le monde. Si un pays jouit d'une bonne image, comme l'Allemagne, la Suède ou la Suisse, tout est facile et rien n'est cher. Il y a plus de touristes. Plus d'investisseurs. Vous vendez vos produits plus chers. Par contre, si vous avez un pays avec une image très faible ou négative, tout est difficile et tout est cher. Les gouvernements s'inquiètent donc de l'image de leur pays, car elle influence directement leurs rentrées d'argent, et c'est ce qu'ils se sont engagés à fournir à leur peuple. Il y a deux ans, j'ai décidé de faire une pause et de m'adresser à cette immense base de données et de lui demander pourquoi certains préfèrent un pays à un autre. La réponse de la base de données m'a complètement sidéré. C'était 6,8. Je n'ai pas le temps d'expliquer en détail. En gros, ce qu'elle m'a dit, c'était... (Rires) (Applaudissements) les pays que nous préférons sont les bons pays. Nous n'admirons pas un pays parce qu'il est riche, puissant, ou qu'il a du succès, parce qu'il est moderne, à la pointe de la technologie, nous admirons surtout un pays parce qu'il est bon. Ça veut dire quoi ? Ça veut dire ceux qui contribuent au monde dans lequel nous vivons, les pays qui rendent le monde plus sûr, meilleur, plus riche ou plus juste. Voilà ceux que nous aimons. Cette découverte est capitale, vous voyez où je veux en venir, parce que ça règle le problème. Je dis désormais aux gouvernements « pour réussir, vous devez faire le bien. » Si vous voulez vendre plus, obtenir plus d'investissement, si vous voulez devenir plus compétitif, vous devez bien vous comporter. Ainsi, vous gagnerez le respect, et on voudra faire des affaires avec vous. Donc, plus vous collaborez, plus vous devenez compétitif. C'est une découverte assez importante, et dès lors, j'ai senti qu'il fallait un autre indice. Plus je vieillis et plus mes idées sont simples et enfantines, apparemment. Celui-ci s'appelle « l'indice des bons pays », et tout est dit dans le titre. Il mesure, ou du moins essaie de mesurer, la contribution exacte de chaque pays, pas à ses propres habitants, mais au reste de l'humanité. Étrangement, personne n'avait pensé à le mesurer avant. Mon collègue Robert Govers et moi-même avons donc passé ces deux années, avec l'aide de nombreuses personnes très sérieuses et intelligentes, à rassembler toutes les données fiables nous indiquant ce que les différents pays offrent au monde. Et vous voulez que je vous dise lequel se démarque. Et je vais vous le dire, mais d'abord je veux expliquer ce que j'entends exactement par « bon pays ». Je ne parle pas de bien moral. Si je dis que tel ou tel pays est le « plus bon » pays au monde, et pas le « meilleur », « meilleur », c'est différent. En parlant d'un bon pays, il y a « bon », « plus bon » et « le plus bon ». Ce n'est pas « bien », « mieux » et « meilleur ». C'est un pays qui, tout simplement, donne plus à l'humanité que tous les autres pays. Pas ce qu'ils font chez eux, ça c'est mesuré par d'autres indices. Et le grand gagnant est... L'Irlande. (Applaudissements) Selon les données que j'ai ici, aucun pays dans le monde, que ce soit par habitant, ou par dollar de PIB, ne contribue plus à notre monde que l'Irlande. Ça veut dire quoi ? Ça veut dire qu'avant de s'endormir, quelques secondes avant de sombrer, on devrait tous se dire : « Mince, heureusement qu'il y a l'Irlande. » (Rires) Et ça... (Applaudissements) Alors que nous traversons une grave récession économique, je pense qu'il y a vraiment une leçon à en tirer : arriver à honorer ses devoirs internationaux tout en reconstruisant sa propre économie ça force l'admiration. La Finlande est très proche. Elle est derrière l'Irlande parce que son plus bas score est inférieur à celui de l'Irlande. Une autre chose à propos de ce top 10 : tous ces pays, sauf la Nouvelle-Zélande, sont des pays d'Europe occidentale. Ils sont également tous riches. Ça m'a déçu, parce que je redoutais notamment de découvrir avec cet indice que seuls les pays riches peuvent aider les pays pauvres. Ce n'est pas le cas. Et d'ailleurs, un peu plus bas, je n'ai pas la diapo sur moi, vous verrez quelque chose qui m'a vraiment réjoui, c'est que le Kenya est dans le top 30, et ça prouve une chose très, très importante : ce n'est pas l'argent qui compte. C'est l'attitude. C'est la culture. C'est un gouvernement et un peuple qui veulent contribuer au reste du monde et qui ont de l'imagination et le courage de se tourner vers les autres, plutôt que de ne penser qu'à eux. Je vais vite passer les autres diapos pour vous montrer les pays moins bien classés. On a l'Allemagne en 13e place, les États-Unis à la 21e place, le Mexique à la 66e place, et là on a des pays en voie de développement comme la Russie à la 95e place, ou la Chine à la 107e place. Pour les pays comme la Chine, la Russie ou l'Inde, qui se trouve à peu près au même niveau, en quelque sorte, ça ne m'étonne pas. Ils ont passé beaucoup de temps récemment, à construire leur propre économie, leur propre société et leur propre constitution. Mais on peut espérer que leur croissance se tournera ensuite plus vers l'extérieur que ça a été le cas jusqu'à présent. On peut aussi se pencher sur chaque pays pour voir toutes ses données en détail. Vous y aurez accès à partir de ce soir, minuit, sur goodcountry.org, pour consulter les détails. Vous pouvez même voir le niveau de chaque donnée individuelle. Donc ça, c'est l'indice des bons pays. Ça sert à quoi ? Eh bien, il existe car je veux essayer d'injecter le mot « bon », ou de le réinjecter, dans la conversation. J'en ai assez d'entendre parler de compétitivité. J'en ai assez d'entendre parler de prospérité, de richesse, de croissance rapide. J'en ai assez d'entendre parler de pays heureux parce que ça reste quand même égoïste. Nous restons tournés vers nous-mêmes, et si on continue comme ça, nous aurons de gros, gros problèmes. Je crois qu'on sait tous ce qu'on veut entendre. On veut entendre parler de bons pays, et je vais d'ailleurs vous demander un petit service. C'est pas grand chose. Ce sera peut-être facile à faire, peut-être même agréable ou même utile : c'est de commencer à employer le mot « bon » dans ce contexte. Quand vous pensez à votre propre pays, quand vous pensez aux pays des autres, quand vous pensez à des sociétés, quand vous parlez du monde d'aujourd'hui, mettez-vous à employer ce mot de la façon dont j'en ai parlé ce soir. Pas « bon », le contraire de « mauvais », parce que c'est trop subjectif. Mais « bon », le contraire d' « égoïste », pour qualifier un pays qui s'intéresse aux intérêts de tous. J'aimerais que vous essayiez, que ce mot devienne le bâton qui s'abattrait sur nos politiciens. Quand vous élisez, que vous les réélisez, que vous votez pour eux, que vous écoutez ce qu'ils vous proposent, employez ce mot, « bon », et posez-vous la question : « Est-ce qu'un bon pays ferait ça ? » Et si la réponse est non, méfiez-vous. Posez-vous la question : « C'est ça, le comportement de mon pays ? » « Est-ce que je veux venir d'un pays où le gouvernement, en mon nom, fait de telles choses ? Ou est-ce que je préfère plutôt voyager aux quatre coins du monde la tête haute, en me disant que je suis fier d'être originaire d'un bon pays ? » Et tout le monde vous accueillera. Et tout le monde, avant de dormir, quelques secondes avant de sombrer, se dira : « Mince, heureusement qu'il y a ce pays. » Je pense que c'est ça, au bout du compte, qui fera changer les choses. Ce mot, « bon », et le nombre 6,8 ainsi que la découverte qui se cache derrière ont changé ma vie. Ils peuvent changer votre vie, et ils peuvent nous permettre de changer le comportement des politiciens et des sociétés, et ainsi, nous pourrons changer le monde. La façon dont je vois mon pays a changé depuis que je pense à ces choses-là. Avant, je voulais vivre dans un pays riche, et puis j'ai voulu vivre dans un pays heureux, mais j'ai ensuite compris que ça ne suffisait pas. Je ne veux pas vivre dans un pays riche. Je ne veux pas vivre dans un pays en forte croissance, ou dans un pays compétitif. Je veux vivre dans un bon pays. Et j'espère vraiment que vous aussi. Merci. (Applaudissements)